<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title>ntlk&#8217;s blog</title>
  <link href="http://ntlk.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ntlk.net/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-22T09:38:20+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://ntlk.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name>ntlk</name>
    
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title>South by South East</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2012/08/21/south-by-south-east"/>
    <updated>2012-08-21T23:22:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2012/08/21/south-by-south-east</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you live in or near Brighton, September is going to be like Christmas. No, wait, it&amp;#8217;s going to be better than Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 3rd of September you&amp;#8217;d be forgiven for thinking you&amp;#8217;ve suddenly found yourself in the middle of South by South… er… East&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;. Monday kicks off with &lt;a href=&quot;http://reasonstobecreative.com/&quot;&gt;Reasons to be Creative&lt;/a&gt;, a 3 day conference/festival for artists, designers and coders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s followed by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lighthouse.org.uk/programme/improving-reality&quot;&gt;Improving Reality&lt;/a&gt; on Thursday, a one day conference discussing how new technologies change our understanding of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Improving Reality we&amp;#8217;ve got &lt;a href=&quot;http://brightonsf.adactio.com/&quot;&gt;Brighton SF&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eventbrite.com/event/3530719477?ref=ebtnebtckt&quot;&gt;Thursday evening&lt;/a&gt;, a panel discussion and readings from leading SF authors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then on Friday it&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://2012.dconstruct.org/&quot;&gt;dConstruct&lt;/a&gt;: this year&amp;#8217;s theme is &amp;#8220;Playing With The Future&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Saturday the 8th &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.makerfairebrighton.com/&quot;&gt;Brighton Mini Maker Faire&lt;/a&gt; opens its doors. It&amp;#8217;s a one day celebration of all things made: arts, crafts, robotics, engineering, woodwork, electronics, science music and more. Last year&amp;#8217;s Faire was so well received it has expanded a bit. This year we will have some &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.makerfairebrighton.com/2012/08/21/introducing-the-speakers/&quot;&gt;speaking sessions&lt;/a&gt; from makers who will lift the lid on their creative process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speakers include &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.makielab.com/who-we-are/&quot;&gt;Alice Taylor&lt;/a&gt; (also at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lighthouse.org.uk/programme/improving-reality&quot;&gt;Improving Reality&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;http://berglondon.com/studio/matt-webb/&quot;&gt;Matt Webb&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://finalbullet.com/&quot;&gt;Leila Johnston&lt;/a&gt; (speaking at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lighthouse.org.uk/programme/improving-reality&quot;&gt;Improving Reality&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;http://codeclub.org.uk/&quot;&gt;Code Club&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://infovore.org/&quot;&gt;Tom Armitage&lt;/a&gt; (also speaking at &lt;a href=&quot;http://2012.dconstruct.org/&quot;&gt;dConstruct&lt;/a&gt;), and students from Cavendish School and Dorothy Stringer. It&amp;#8217;s a free event starting at 3pm in the Founders Room of the Brighton Dome, so come in early to make sure you get a seat. Oh, did I mention it was free? Don&amp;#8217;t miss it. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.makerfairebrighton.com/2012/08/21/introducing-the-speakers/&quot;&gt;More details here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*)&lt;/sup&gt; I blame &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/honorharger&quot;&gt;@honorharger&lt;/a&gt; for this terrible joke.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>A few thoughts on Happenstance so far</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2012/05/25/a-few-thoughts-on-happenstance-so-far"/>
    <updated>2012-05-25T18:07:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2012/05/25/a-few-thoughts-on-happenstance-so-far</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lighthouse.org.uk/&quot;&gt;Lighthouse&lt;/a&gt; we (the Lighthouse team + the &lt;a href=&quot;http://happenstanceproject.com&quot;&gt;Happenstance&lt;/a&gt; residents &amp;amp; organisers) held an Open House event, talking to our guests about some of the work me and &lt;a href=&quot;http://shorttermmemoryloss.com/&quot;&gt;James&lt;/a&gt; have done on the project so far and what &lt;a href=&quot;http://happenstanceproject.com&quot;&gt;Happenstance&lt;/a&gt; is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://ntlk.net/images/oh1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happenstance brings together technologists and arts organisations to infuse the latter with the technological understanding and innovative approaches of the former. Putting people together in the same room is a remarkably simple yet underrated idea. Running the experiment three times in three different organisations hopefully will show which parts of it can be replicated and which were just a fluke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Lighthouse team have been using a tool for recording team processes me and James have built – &lt;a href=&quot;http://happenstanceproject.com/say-hi-to-offbott/&quot;&gt;Offbott&lt;/a&gt; – for a while, I suggested doing daily stand-up meetings and banning email for internal communications, in the spirit of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.agilemanifesto.org/&quot;&gt;Agile manifesto&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#8217;s been interesting for me to find out this way exactly how everyone works and what their work involves, though of course I had hoped this would also prove equally interesting to everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8165/7261135608_64f960c24b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Agile.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everyone always works on the same projects together, and knowing what everyone else does and how they do it is useful. I would like to think I&amp;#8217;ve contributed to the understanding the value of inspecting your processes and seeking ways to improve them through reflection and discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second (and last!) Open House even will be held on Tuesday 19 June at &lt;a href=&quot;http://lighthouse.org.uk/&quot;&gt;Lighthouse&lt;/a&gt;. Do come along to hear more.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Building the Future</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2012/05/08/building-the-future"/>
    <updated>2012-05-08T15:40:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2012/05/08/building-the-future</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://ntlk.net/images/design_vacuum.png&quot; alt=&quot;One does not simply design in a vacuum&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graduating from a design course at Goldsmiths bestowed me with a sense of power and a sense of responsibility. You don&amp;#8217;t casually design stuff that will affect people&amp;#8217;s lives without stopping first to think about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;re finally collectively waking up to the fact that the tools of the future are largely software tools. I design and make digital things - they can sometimes seem like not real things at all. They appear so ethereal that my parents struggle to describe to friends and family what it is I do for a living. And yet with every design decision, every small feature, or lack of feature, or way of doing things - I know it can affect how people relate to one another. &lt;a href=&quot;http://farmerandfarmer.org/medicine/future.html&quot;&gt;Jonathan Harris&lt;/a&gt; predicts the burden of responsibility is about to get heavier - eventually the software will be followed by hardware embedded in our bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Software is the staging ground for the future, affording us the time and space to get our ethics right, before the stakes are raised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, the way these biological interventions will happen is that there will be some guy who starts a company, and he will have a small design team, and they will make certain choices, and decisions around things like default settings, and they will build their product, and release it into the world, and early adopters will adopt it, and then ordinary folks will try it too, and soon thereafter the physical bodies of millions of people will forever be augmented by the flippant choices made on a Tuesday afternoon in a little sunny room in Palo Alto. [source: &lt;a href=&quot;http://farmerandfarmer.org/medicine/index.html&quot;&gt;Farmer and Farmer, Essays About Humans and Technology&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is why I&amp;#8217;m worried, and so should you be, because it means your life in the future is being decided by people who may have very little in common with you, and may not understand your needs at all. Worse: they may not even care. Even worse: they may see profit in actively working against your needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Case in point: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nymwars&quot;&gt;Google+ nymwars&lt;/a&gt;. Not long after its launch, Google decided to start shutting down profiles of people who didn&amp;#8217;t use their real names to sign up to the service. On one hand of course they have a right to do that, it&amp;#8217;s their business after all to know everything about you so they can adequately price your eyeballs. At the same time, due to their size and prominence, shouldn&amp;#8217;t large companies feel responsible about decisions they make becoming the de facto standard? &amp;#8220;Waah, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Pseudonymity&quot;&gt;pseudonymity&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Anonymity&quot;&gt;anonymity&lt;/a&gt; are only for BAD people who have something to hide&amp;#8221; - I hear you think, but before you say it, check if you can see yourself on this &lt;a href=&quot;http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Who_is_harmed_by_a_%22Real_Names%22_policy%3F&quot;&gt;very long list of people that are harmed by real name policies&lt;/a&gt;. We might find ourselves in twenty years time with a stifled freedom of expression, because we fell for a straw-man argument against one real, unified identity online - argument that someone created to make profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology is often perceived as somewhat scientific and objective, especially by non-technical audiences. I&amp;#8217;ve come to think this is a lie. Recently, I saw &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scottporad.com/&quot;&gt;Scott Porad&lt;/a&gt; speak about it at &lt;a href=&quot;http://devslovebacon.com/&quot;&gt;Bacon&lt;/a&gt;. &amp;#8220;Software is a reflection of people and processes that created it&amp;#8221;, he argued, and I wholeheartedly agreed. And it&amp;#8217;s not just the software. Everywhere where decisions made that have an effect on other people - there will be biases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But biases don&amp;#8217;t always have to be a bad thing. Many tools and technologies in existence express positive values: pursuit of happiness, real human connection, attempts to fix difficult problems. Some contributors do so in their spare time, only rewarded with gratitude and sense of satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge is to empower more people to actively participate in thinking about and building TEH FUTURE. So why not &lt;a href=&quot;http://codingforkids.org/wiki/Main_Page&quot;&gt;teach kids to code&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kapipal.com/760573d1b2ec4ecab351982e9122ce2f&quot;&gt;help others do so&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>On the New Aesthetic</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2012/04/12/on-the-new-aesthetic"/>
    <updated>2012-04-12T10:38:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2012/04/12/on-the-new-aesthetic</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After Bruce Sterling published &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/beyond_the_beyond/2012/04/an-essay-on-the-new-aesthetic/&quot;&gt;his essay&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://new-aesthetic.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;New Aesthetic&lt;/a&gt; last Monday, the topic exploded and responses to that essay were as quick as they were plentiful (see below for links). Suddenly it became a hotly debated subject on Twitter, so I thought what everyone desperately needed was - yep - yet another blog post on the New Aesthetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.g-truc.net/post/0448-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gerhard Richter, 4096 colours, 1974&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Gerhard Richter, 4096 colours, 1974&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week I’ve been to &lt;a href=&quot;http://michelle.kasprzak.ca/blog/&quot;&gt;Michelle Kasprzak&lt;/a&gt;’s brilliant &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lighthouse.org.uk/programme/monthly-talk-michelle-kasprzak?query=kasprzak&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; about new artistic frontiers and works made possible by recent leaps in technological advancement. It included a critique of the New Aesthetic as an art movement, pointing out its main flaw: that much of it is not new. She presented evidence of works of art from the twentieth century that could easily be thought of as belonging to the NA, but predating it. One of the examples was Gerhard Richter’s painting resembling pixels today (as we’ve learned to understand a grid of squares), painted in 1974. It’s true that some of the visual language present in items collected on the NA Tumblr existed before. What’s really been bothering me is that I don’t think that NA is an art movement at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, some of the things in the NA collection are undeniably works of art (like &lt;a href=&quot;http://new-aesthetic.tumblr.com/post/16174636454/the-project-was-based-on-data-i-gathered-by-taking&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://new-aesthetic.tumblr.com/post/17163297795/investigating-the-rotation-of-data-these&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://new-aesthetic.tumblr.com/post/20895023430/cardboard-papercraft-sculpture-created-from-3d&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;). But what this collection says to me is this: we already live in the reality where digital and physical are beginning to blend. The visual language of the machines we built is seeping into our consciousness and affecting our aesthetic preferences. We see beauty in limitations of visual artefacts produced by our tools. We already share a world with autonomous machines, and we adapt it so they can survive alongside us. It’s a body of evidence not only that the future has arrived already, but that we are already so familiar with its visual representations that we almost don’t notice there’s anything odd with it entering the physical realm.  It’s inevitable that an art movement (or maybe a number of them) can be found within the collection, but as a whole it’s bigger than this - it covers a much broader cultural area. It’s as much about art as it is about the everyday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, in itself, this isn’t anything new. Similar shifts in aesthetics have happened before, time and time again, because our technologies, as they become prevalent, always make their mark on our aesthetic sensibilities and our understanding of the world. Yesterday it was the industrialisation, today it’s computing. We always see the world through our tools. Today it’s through the eyes of tools that begin to see for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://madelineashby.com/?p=1198&quot;&gt;The New Aesthetic of the male gaze&lt;/a&gt; - by &lt;a href=&quot;http://madelineashby.com/&quot;&gt;Madeline Ashby&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://metalab.harvard.edu/2012/04/but-it-moves-the-new-aesthetic-emergent-virtual-taste/&quot;&gt;But it moves: the New Aesthetic &amp;amp; emergent virtual taste&lt;/a&gt; - by Matthew Battles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://remus-shepherd.livejournal.com/354140.html&quot;&gt;The New Aesthetic, and what’s next&lt;/a&gt; - by Remus Shepherd&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thecreatorsproject.com/blog/in-response-to-bruce-sterlings-essay-on-the-new-aesthetic&quot;&gt;In Response To Bruce Sterling’s &amp;#8220;Essay On The New Aesthetic&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Beginning a residency at the Lighthouse as a technologist - Happenstance Project</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2012/04/02/beginning-a-residency-at-the-lighthouse-as-a-technologist"/>
    <updated>2012-04-02T10:47:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2012/04/02/beginning-a-residency-at-the-lighthouse-as-a-technologist</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Until the end of June I am a &lt;a href=&quot;http://happenstanceproject.com/&quot;&gt;resident technologist&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lighthouse.org.uk/&quot;&gt;Lighthouse&lt;/a&gt; in Brighton, together with &lt;a href=&quot;http://shorttermmemoryloss.com/&quot;&gt;James Bridle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lighthouse is an interesting organisation - it describes itself as a digital culture agency, rather than simply a digital arts agency, emphasising its broad interests that go beyond the arts sector. It&amp;#8217;s an organisation that is forward looking and welcomes the challenges presented by technology. Perhaps this is why they are confident enough to let me and James drive the process without necessarily having a clear idea of the outcome (or direction) just yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their openness was what attracted me to the project. I could work using the process in which you gradually narrow your problem space to eventually define the project&amp;#8217;s objectives is what they would like to happen. This kind of approach from my experience can result in something much more interesting than when the outcome is clearly defined at the beginning. While it may not be suitable for every type of project, it feels exactly right for &lt;a href=&quot;http://happenstanceproject.com/&quot;&gt;Happenstance&lt;/a&gt;, where the goals are much wider than simply delivering a product. You can probably tell by now that I am excited about having an opportunity to further develop my practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;#8217;t worked with any arts organisations before, so it will be interesting to find out more about the work they do and how they do it. Lighthouse not only exhibits existing work, but also acts in a commissioning capacity, as well as doing administrative and supportive work that is largely hidden from public view. Any impact that this project will have on the way Lighthouse operates will be felt by many more organisations, so this is a brilliant opportunity to do something great… no pressure then!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Crossposted from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://happenstanceproject.com/working-at-the-lighthouse/&quot;&gt;Happenstance blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Drawing robots roundup</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2012/01/15/drawing-robots-roundup"/>
    <updated>2012-01-15T09:58:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2012/01/15/drawing-robots-roundup</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I intend to build a drawing robot soon as a part of a bigger project that will hopefully culminate in a short animation. I have just been given a broken HP Deskjet D4260 so I already have a few parts I might need. I am not yet fully decided on which approach to take, so here&amp;#8217;s a roundup of different drawing machines to inspire me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Der Kritzler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://player.vimeo.com/video/28003302?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Have I mentioned yet how much I love &lt;a href=&quot;http://tinkerlog.com/&quot;&gt;Alex Weber&amp;#8217;s projects&lt;/a&gt;? The one that led me to find his blog was &lt;a href=&quot;http://tinkerlog.com/2011/09/02/der-kritzler/&quot;&gt;Der Kritzler&lt;/a&gt; - a robot that draws on the windows. It uses a combination of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.processing.org/&quot;&gt;Processing&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imagemagick.org/script/index.php&quot;&gt;ImageMagick&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://potrace.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;Potrace&lt;/a&gt; to create the graphics and the movement of the bot itself is controlled by an Arduino. The device is suspended on notched tape which controls the movements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Hektor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://player.vimeo.com/video/15823044?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;375&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hektor.ch/&quot;&gt;Hektor&lt;/a&gt; was the project that made me fall in love with physical hacking, it&amp;#8217;s the first one of its kind that I could find - built in 2002. It&amp;#8217;s a small portable spraypainting device that can cover a huge wall area, but packs away into a small suitcase. Its construction directly inspired Der Kritzler - the spraycan&amp;#8217;s movements are controlled by toothed belts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Delta Robot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://player.vimeo.com/video/25924581?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;375&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Arduino-controlled suspended plotter. 3 arms are controlled by servos. I like this one a lot despite the lack of precision. Its creator, &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/117437757896877369617&quot;&gt;Puiu Bogdan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://arduino.cc/forum/index.php/topic,65561.0.html&quot;&gt;explains&lt;/a&gt; that the concept itself results in very precise drawings, but his implementation still needs to be perfected. Since it took him 7 months to build this prototype I reckon it&amp;#8217;s a little too complicated for my purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;3-Axis servo motor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;339&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/v9x7Qdpp43M&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Definitely can&amp;#8217;t make anything similar as I intend to use mine at home, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.embeddedtronics.com/uhuservo.html&quot;&gt;this is cool&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Senseless Drawing Robot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://player.vimeo.com/video/30780208?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://thisisnotagraffiti.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;This bot&lt;/a&gt; built by &lt;a href=&quot;http://kannoso.org/&quot;&gt;So Kanno&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://yang02.org/&quot;&gt;Takahiro Yamaguchi&lt;/a&gt; uses a double-pendulum to randomise its graphic output. Pretty awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Polargraph&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://player.vimeo.com/video/24647023?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;375&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;iframe width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;339&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/UT8p1kLz8PI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/user/euphyscott&quot;&gt;Euphyscott&lt;/a&gt; made this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.polargraph.co.uk/&quot;&gt;polargraph&lt;/a&gt;. Although it&amp;#8217;s very slow in drawing these types of images, the end result is pretty neat. Also, bonus points for posting the code and detailed process descriptions on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.polargraph.co.uk/&quot;&gt;polargraph&amp;#8217;s website&lt;/a&gt; and on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.instructables.com/id/Polargraph-Drawing-Machine/&quot;&gt;Instructables&lt;/a&gt;. You can also &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.polargraph.co.uk/build-or-buy-a-machine/&quot;&gt;buy some of the bits used&lt;/a&gt; to build your own from Euphyscott.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Interactive Robotic Painting Machine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://player.vimeo.com/video/23998286&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bengrosser.com/&quot;&gt;Benjamin Grosser&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://bengrosser.com/projects/interactive-robotic-painting-machine/&quot;&gt;creation&lt;/a&gt; listens to its surroundings and the sound input affects the decisions the AI makes in its painting process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Robo-rainbow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://player.vimeo.com/video/19374769?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.akayism.org/&quot;&gt;Akay&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8217;s robo-rainbow was featured in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.co.uk/news/archive/2011-02/02/robo-rainbow&quot;&gt;Wired&lt;/a&gt; last year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;A small circuit board featuring radio-controlled servos from a toy car drives the solenoids attached to each spray can, which in turn apply pressure to the nozzles. Both the arm and the spray cans are controlled using toy car&amp;#8217;s radio controller, allowing the user to move the arm in a smooth arc while spraying with each of the six spray cans simultaneously, creating a large rainbow painting within seconds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Pen plotter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;object type=&quot;application/x-shockwave-flash&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;375&quot; data=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/apps/video/stewart.swf?v=109786&quot; classid=&quot;clsid:D27CDB6E-AE6D-11cf-96B8-444553540000&quot;&gt; &lt;param name=&quot;flashvars&quot; value=&quot;intl_lang=en-us&amp;photo_secret=3d4e830459&amp;photo_id=6295455826&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt; &lt;param name=&quot;movie&quot; value=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/apps/video/stewart.swf?v=109786&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt; &lt;param name=&quot;bgcolor&quot; value=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt; &lt;param name=&quot;allowFullScreen&quot; value=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed type=&quot;application/x-shockwave-flash&quot; src=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/apps/video/stewart.swf?v=109786&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#000000&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; flashvars=&quot;intl_lang=en-us&amp;photo_secret=3d4e830459&amp;photo_id=6295455826&quot; height=&quot;375&quot; width=&quot;500&quot;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm7.staticflickr.com/6218/6294759696_7ed5be13f1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pen plotter image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And last but not least, my favourite, built by &lt;a href=&quot;http://interlockroc.org/author/berticus/&quot;&gt;Berticus&lt;/a&gt;. This &lt;a href=&quot;http://interlockroc.org/2011/10/30/barcamp-rochester/&quot;&gt;pen plotter&lt;/a&gt; traces input from the webcam to create some really awesome &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/bert_m_b/sets/72157628015314436/with/6294759696/&quot;&gt;portraits&lt;/a&gt;. Just look at them!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Olly, the smelly robot</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2012/01/14/olly-the-smelly-robot"/>
    <updated>2012-01-14T10:26:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2012/01/14/olly-the-smelly-robot</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;iframe frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;400px&quot; src=&quot;http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1209578799/olly-the-web-connected-smelly-robot/widget/video.html&quot; width=&quot;500px&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My lovely friends &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/Bredford2&quot;&gt;Ben Redford&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ofmyownaccord.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Chris Thomas&lt;/a&gt; have been working on this little bot at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mintdigital.com/&quot;&gt;Mint Digital&lt;/a&gt;. They&amp;#8217;ve even kept a &lt;a href=&quot;http://foundry.mintdigital.com/&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; to document their explorations and process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is now on Kickstarter, so if you like the idea of smelling your online notifications you should check out their &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1209578799/olly-the-web-connected-smelly-robot&quot;&gt;project page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Discussing digital literacy on Techgrumps</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2011/12/30/discussing-digital-literacy-on-techgrumps"/>
    <updated>2011-12-30T18:27:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2011/12/30/discussing-digital-literacy-on-techgrumps</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last night I was talking about teaching digital skills to kids with some very smart people on Techgrumps. You can find the podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://techgrumps.wordpress.com/2011/12/29/techgrumps-51-noncomputing-for-generation-t/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Poetrybin</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2011/11/27/poetrybin"/>
    <updated>2011-11-27T16:18:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2011/11/27/poetrybin</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few days ago I saw &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/unhaunting/status/139422971172368384&quot;&gt;this tweet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7166/6412166473_7b7edbf00e.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Internet identities were on my mind for a while. Most services we use require signing up, some with your real-life name and address, forbidding you from creating multiple personas for multiple facets of your personality. Having to prove who I am every time I want to talk to friends is &lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: line-through&quot;&gt;a bit&lt;/span&gt; exactly like having to show my papers every time I speak, and having it logged by a third party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch moot talk about these issues. He&amp;#8217;s really inspiring, and I completely agree with him: we need more choices in how our identities are represented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;339&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/nbPASJiAfu4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wish there were more spaces where you didn&amp;#8217;t have to create and maintain a persona. 4chan is just one example and I appreciate that some people may not like what goes on there. So in an attempt to redress the balance at least a tiny bit I made &lt;a href=&quot;http://poetrybin.heroku.com&quot;&gt;Poetrybin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premise is simple: there are no identities, no user accounts. You can post a poem, but you cannot edit or delete it. That&amp;#8217;s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://poetrybin.heroku.com&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7022/6412216653_edd31767d7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Convert RGB to HSB (HSV) in Ruby</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2011/11/21/convert-rgb-to-hsb-hsv-in-ruby"/>
    <updated>2011-11-21T19:40:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2011/11/21/convert-rgb-to-hsb-hsv-in-ruby</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I needed to convert RGB values into HSB. I found a very old gem, &lt;a href=&quot;http://rubygems.org/gems/color-tools&quot;&gt;colour-tools&lt;/a&gt;, which sadly only converts to HSL. So I rewrote &lt;a href=&quot;http://forums.devshed.com/c-programming-42/rgb-to-hsv-conversion-rountine-162526.html&quot;&gt;Alvein&amp;#8217;s C implementation&lt;/a&gt; to calculate it in Ruby. Hope it saves someone time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inputs: red, green and blue values as integers between 0 and 255. Outputs according to HSB convention: hue as degrees (up to 360), saturation and brightness as percentages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;script src=&#8217;https://gist.github.com/1383603.js?file=&#8217;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Input rgb values 1&#8230;255
# based on http://forums.devshed.com/c-programming-42/rgb-to-hsv-conversion-rountine-162526.html

r = r / 255.0
g = g / 255.0
b = b / 255.0
max = [r, g, b].max
min = [r, g, b].min
delta = max - min
v = max * 100

if (max != 0.0)
    s = delta / max *100
else
    s = 0.0
end

if (s == 0.0) 
    h = 0.0
else
    if (r == max)
        h = (g - b) / delta
    elsif (g == max)
        h = 2 + (b - r) / delta
    elsif (b == max)
        h = 4 + (r - g) / delta
    end

    h *= 60.0
    
    if (h &amp;lt; 0)
        h += 360.0
    end
end

# returns h in the range of 0..360 deg
# s 0&#8230;100 
# v 0&#8230;100&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;&lt;/div&gt;



</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>New Soul</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2011/10/24/new-soul"/>
    <updated>2011-10-24T21:37:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2011/10/24/new-soul</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://player.vimeo.com/video/30979928?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&amp;amp;color=ffffff&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitAllowFullScreen allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My husband Sam and his team mate Steve have been working on their new album for the last few month. They are looking for some financial help with finishing it. I would love it if you could check out their project on &lt;a href=&quot;http://sponsume.com/project/new-soul-1/&quot;&gt;Sponsume&lt;/a&gt;, and if you like it, please share the link with your friends. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>UX Camp Brighton 2011</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2011/10/02/ux-camp-brighton-2011"/>
    <updated>2011-10-02T17:45:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2011/10/02/ux-camp-brighton-2011</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6171/6204481486_a2838cd0be.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I participated the UX Camp Brighton on Saturday, which took place in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cogapp.com/&quot;&gt;Cogapp&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt; office. How do you guys get any work done with a view like this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6176/6204498904_1d094b44e2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite it being the warmest and most beautiful day we had this year, the turnout was impressive and I got to see some great talks and participated in though-provoking discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.glennjones.net/&quot;&gt;Glenn Jones&lt;/a&gt; raised a very important point about &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_Intents&quot;&gt;web intents&lt;/a&gt; - that the language we use to describe them will have a huge impact on the success of this initiative. The terms used need to be universally understood, and this already presents challenges. I thoroughly recommend Glenn&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://glennjones.net/2011/08/web-intentsgluing-web-functionality-together/&quot;&gt;blog post about web intents&lt;/a&gt;, it&amp;#8217;s a brilliant introduction to the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/eldevri&quot;&gt;Ellen de Vries&lt;/a&gt; made us bond with with bits of rubbish by giving them names and a back story. &lt;a href=&quot;http://paulo72.com/&quot;&gt;Paul Davison&lt;/a&gt; gave us an introduction to microdata, &lt;a href=&quot;http://andyhume.net/&quot;&gt;Andy Hume&lt;/a&gt; pointed out that making urls friendly to the extreme isn&amp;#8217;t always the best approach, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cennydd.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Cennydd Bowles&lt;/a&gt; kicked off a discussion about the role of UX, what it really means and whether it is different from product design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;ve missed out on tickets to UX Camp you might be interested in &lt;a href=&quot;http://designjambrighton.eventbrite.com/&quot;&gt;Design Jam&lt;/a&gt;, which is also a free event, but will give you a chance to do something practical.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>If in doubt use more glowstone</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2011/09/27/if-in-doubt-use-more-glowstone"/>
    <updated>2011-09-27T23:46:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2011/09/27/if-in-doubt-use-more-glowstone</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntlk.net/images/minecraft-tree-1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://ntlk.net/images/minecraft-tree-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntlk.net/images/minecraft-tree-3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://ntlk.net/images/minecraft-tree-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite thing to do in Minecraft is to build things. I used to either keep hacking the inventory or give myself resources 64 blocks at a time while on the server. Since 1.8 update I got my mojo back, as I can just switch on the Creative mode while in Multiplayer. It gives you unlimited blocks and you can fly. I couldn&amp;#8217;t ask for more.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Say hello in comments</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2011/09/25/say-hello-in-comments"/>
    <updated>2011-09-25T18:02:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2011/09/25/say-hello-in-comments</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Comments are now enabled on this blog on each post page. Be nice or get zapped.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Brighton Mini Maker Faire</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2011/09/24/brighton-mini-maker-faire"/>
    <updated>2011-09-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2011/09/24/brighton-mini-maker-faire</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6203/6112868140_9f7c4c4ab0.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s been nearly three weeks since, but I haven&amp;#8217;t had the chance to grab a moment to write about the wonderful event that was the first Brighton Mini Maker Faire. It was a truly exciting festival of experimentation, creativity and discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6197/6112903988_f6e5b39d7f.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite projects was the drawing robot. As the model sits down to be sketched, a tiny camera turns to their face and takes a snapshot from which to work. A robotic arm draws the model&amp;#8217;s face in strange, sketchy movements that slowly build up the drawing. Periodically, the arm stops and the camera turns from paper to model&amp;#8217;s face, pretending to have another look. I was to be honest more excited about that humanised interaction between the person and the machine than I was about the technical challenges of making a drawing arm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6075/6112309523_63b83a1ceb.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running soldering drop-in was the highlight of the day for me. I had the chance to show kids how to put together some electronic kits and watch them own me when it comes to my soldering skills. Heck, I even offered &lt;a href=&quot;http://adactio.com/&quot;&gt;adactio&lt;/a&gt; a quick soldering lesson (no, he didn&amp;#8217;t take it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6084/6112843667_620efcf842.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to say thank you to everyone who got involved in organising it and everyone who turned up on the day to look at and play with some amazing creations! We&amp;#8217;re told more than 5000 people came through the door. None of this would have been possible without a massive group of volunteers, and organisers who have taken on a huge challenge and worked for months to make it happen. Let&amp;#8217;s hope next year we can make it even bigger.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Riotwiki</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2011/08/14/riotwiki"/>
    <updated>2011-08-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2011/08/14/riotwiki</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Often as a group we have a greater capacity for understanding than when we act as individuals, especially when confronted with issues of great complexity. This is why I think &lt;a href=&quot;http://riotwiki.wikispaces.com/&quot;&gt;riotwiki&lt;/a&gt;, collecting information about the 2011 UK riots, is a very good idea. If you can, please participate in creating a full account of what happened.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Boredlondon Twitter bot</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2011/07/31/boredlondon-twitterbot"/>
    <updated>2011-07-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2011/07/31/boredlondon-twitterbot</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Part of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ntlk/boredlondon&quot;&gt;final undergraduate project was&lt;/a&gt; an experiment where I used a Twitter bot to reach a large audience in a short time. I wanted to see if people can be stimulated to action (and if so, how). &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ntlk/boredlondon&quot;&gt;The source&lt;/a&gt; is on Github, so you can have a proper look through it. &lt;a href=&quot;http://aerofade.rk.net.nz/&quot;&gt;AeroFade&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.webecologyproject.org/2011/02/complete-source-code-from-socialbots-2011/&quot;&gt;bot which won&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.webecologyproject.org/2011/01/help-robots-take-over-the-internet-the-socialbots-2011-competition/&quot;&gt;Socialbots&lt;/a&gt; competition was a huge inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/boredlondon&quot;&gt;@boredlondon&lt;/a&gt; bot compiles a list of stuff to do in London from various rss feeds, with some free activities thrown into the mix. It then searches for people who say they are bored and (if their geolocation data points to London) it then introduces itself. If they reply (or mention the bot at all), it will give them a suggestion for a random activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, most of the interactions are very well natured and polite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://ntlk.net/images/boredombot1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://ntlk.net/images/boredombot2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though most of the bot&amp;#8217;s suggestions weren&amp;#8217;t what the participants could have hoped for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://ntlk.net/images/boredombot3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://ntlk.net/images/boredombot4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It comes complete with rudimentary logging system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liquid error: No such file or directory - posix_spawnp&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the improvements I should have thought about when I began the experiment was to create a robust system for logging the whole history of bot&amp;#8217;s interactions, including the messages other people send to it. Because of the way the bot was written, its replies to mentions are not strictly &lt;em&gt;replies&lt;/em&gt; (they are not linked as a part of conversation), the bot remembers the names of people who talk to it and sends them a random suggestion (code fragment edited for clarity):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liquid error: No such file or directory - posix_spawnp&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes it very hard to archive the &lt;em&gt;conversations&lt;/em&gt;, and sadly I haven&amp;#8217;t been doing it. I wish I had done it some other way. I would have been nice to keep track of how many replies are positive, negative, and rude; as well as noting down how many participants say they are likely to take up the suggestion. Any analysis and insights from the experiment seem anecdotal without the hard data to back it up.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Sound installations by Studio Zimoun</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2011/07/09/sound-installations-by-studio-zimoun"/>
    <updated>2011-07-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2011/07/09/sound-installations-by-studio-zimoun</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://player.vimeo.com/video/23574715?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&amp;amp;color=ffffff&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;




&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://player.vimeo.com/video/24262931?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&amp;amp;color=ffffff&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Feasting my eyes and ears on these. &lt;a href=&quot;http://zimoun.ch&quot;&gt;Zimoun&lt;/a&gt; specialises in creating sound installations generated by mechanical movements. Many of his works use rotating motors to bump small objects against each other. Result is strangely organic and captivating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many more fantastic videos of his work on &lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/zimoun&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;. Well worth a look.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Constellation</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2011/07/09/constellation"/>
    <updated>2011-07-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2011/07/09/constellation</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;iframe width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;314&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/VRf7slf6XfY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kinetic-lights.com/index.php?men=projects&amp;amp;sub=constellation&quot;&gt;Constellation&lt;/a&gt; – a light installation by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.whitevoid.com/&quot;&gt;WhiteVoid&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Writing with light</title>
    <link href="http://ntlk.net/2011/07/05/writing-with-light"/>
    <updated>2011-07-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ntlk.net/2011/07/05/writing-with-light</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://ntlk.net/images/Ianto_Makers_02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://i.document.m05.de/&quot;&gt;Michael Zoellner&lt;/a&gt; made a jacket for his dog, Ianto, which sports a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arduino.cc/en/Main/ArduinoBoardLilyPad&quot;&gt;LilyPad&lt;/a&gt; Arduino board and 5 LEDs. When Ianto runs, she creates a very cool looking &lt;a href=&quot;http://i.document.m05.de/?p=970&quot;&gt;light display&lt;/a&gt;. Nice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://ntlk.net/images/Ianto_Makers_05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
